听译、时间轴：刘巍然（学酥）
大家好 欢迎大家回来
Hello, everybody, welcome back.
在上节课中 我们用网站和RPC等例子
In the last lecture, we introduced distributed systems
向大家介绍了分布式系统的概念
by looking at some concrete examples such as the web and RPC,
这两个例子都是客户端/服务端系统
which are examples of client/server systems.
在本节课中 我们将把目光转向
In this lecture, we're going to move things to
更抽象、更泛化的分布式系统模型上
a little bit more abstract and a little bit more general model.
我们将介绍分布式系统的系统模型
And we're going to talk about system models for distributed systems
系统模型指的是分布式系统所满足的假设
which are descriptions of the assumptions that we make
我们要根据这些假设设计适用于分布式系统的算法
when we're designing an algorithm to run in a distributed system.
系统模型非常重要
So, a system model is very important,
我们前面讨论过 分布式系统中会出现很多可能的错误
because as we discussed, things can go wrong in the distributed systems.
节点可能会崩溃 网络可能会故障等
Nodes can crash, networks can fail, and so on.
我们需要准确作出假设 哪些故障情况是可能发生的
And we have to be precise about what failures we are assuming are possible,
哪些故障是不可能发生的
and what failures we are assuming are not possible.
为了引入系统模型的定义
So, we're going to start this
我们先来看看分布式系统中的两个经典思想实验
by looking at two classic thought experiments from distributed systems.
它们分别是两将军问题、拜占庭将军问题
The two generals problem and the byzantine generals problem.
我们先来讲解两将军问题
And we're going to start now with the two generals problem.
两将军问题是用军队打仗的故事来描述的
So, this is kind of like a military analogy.
很抱歉 我不是一个军事迷
I'm sorry about that. I'm not really a big fan of that.
但这个问题就是在军队打仗的背景下描述的
But it's widely known as the two generals problem.
因此我这里也遵守惯例
So, I'm just going to stick with the convention here.
这个思想实验的所描述的场景是
And so, the setting of this thought experiment is that
我们有两支军队每个军队都由一位将军所率领
we have two armies, each army is controlled by one general.
这两个军队希望进攻并占领一座城市
And these armies are wanting to attack and capture a city.
这个城市防守严密
Now, the city is well-defended.
如果同一时间只有一支军队发起进攻 则这只军队会吃败仗
And so, if only one of the armies attacks at one time, that army will get defeated.
因此 很重要的一点是
And so, it's very important that
两位将军都需要发起进攻 两只军队需要同时发起进攻
if the two generals are going to attack, they attack at the same time,
如果两支军队同时发起进攻
because then if both the armies attack at the same time,
则他们就可以获得胜利
they know that they are going to win.
大家可以从这里的真值表看到
So, you can see from this truth table here what happens is
如果两支军队都不发起进攻 那结果也还能接受
OK, it's alright if neither of the two armies attacks,
但如果只有一支军队发起进攻 那事情就变得麻烦了
but if only one of the two armies attacks, then it's all going to go terribly wrong.
我们希望做到的是 当且仅当另一只军队发起进攻时 自己军队才发起进攻
So, what we really want is that one army attacks if and only if the other army attacks.
这样两支军队才能一起进攻
So, both armies attack together.
这里的难点在于
Now, what makes this difficult is that
两位将军无法直接交流并讨论要在什么时候一起进攻
the two generals can't just talk to each other and agree on their plan of when to attack,
他们只能通过信使沟通
but they can only communicate via messengers.
这些信使很辛苦
And so, these messengers,
他们要穿梭在丛林中 为两位将军传递信息
there are people who run with the messengers through the forest,
当他们穿梭在丛林中时 他们可能会被城市的守军抓住
and as they run through the forest, they might get captured by forces of the city.
因此 当一位将军向另一位将军派出一位信使时
And so, whenever one of the generals sends a messenger to the other general,
消息并不一定能传递到另一位将军手中
that message may or may not get through.
发送消息的一方没有任何办法知道
And there's no way for the sender of the message to know
消息是否能成功发送出去
whether the message got through
只有当收到响应时 才能获知消息发送结果
except by receiving a response.
我们现在面对的问题是这样的
And so, the problem here is now this.
举例来说 想象将军1已经决定要在11月10日发起进攻
So, imagine, for example, general 1 has decided to attack on the 10th of November.
因此 他向将军2发送一条消息称
And so, he sends a message to general 2, saying
“我们要在11月10日发起进攻了 你能发起进攻吗？”
“We're going to attack on the 10th November, are you OK with that?”
将军2收到了消息后会说
And general 2 receives the message and says,
“好的 我没问题 我们一起在11月10日发起进攻吧”
“Yes, I'm on board, we're going to attack together on the 10th of November”,
并把响应发送回去
sends that response back.
但很不幸的是 响应消息被截获了
But unfortunately, the response message is captured.
此时 初始的请求消息发送成功 但响应消息丢失了
So, the initial message, the request gets through, but the response is lost.
此时 将军1没有收到响应
And so, now, general 1 does not receive a response.
这是其中一种可能发生的情况
Now, this is one scenario of what could happen.
还有另一种可能发生的情况
Here's another scenario of what could happen.
另一种可能发生的情况是
It could also happen that
将军1向将军2发送消息“在11月10日发起进攻”
general 1 sends the message “Attack on the 10th of November” to general 2.
但初始消息就丢失了 没有发送到将军2那里
But that initial message is lost and never gets through to general 2.
现在 将军2没有收到任何消息 因此他也不会响应消息
And now, general 2 doesn't receive any message. So, he's not going to respond either.
但此时的最终结果仍然是将军1没有收到响应
And the end result is also the general 1 does not receive a response.
因此 在这两种情况下 将军1只能观察到一种结果：没有收到响应
So, in both of these two cases, the only thing that general 1 observes is no response.
但是将军1不知道没有收到响应的原因是什么
But general 1 does not know whether there's no response,
可能是初始消息就没有发送过去 也可能是响应消息丢失了
because the initial message didn't get through, or whether the response was lost.
但这两种情况有一个很大的不同点
But there's a big difference between the two of these,
从将军2的视角看
because from general 2 point of view,
第一种情况下 将军2已经同意共同发起进攻
in the first case, general 2 has agreed to attack,
第二种情况下 将军2甚至不知道要发起进攻了
in the second case, general 2 doesn't even know about the attack.
因此 从将军1的视角看 两种情况的结果是一样的
So, they look the same from general 1’s point of view,
从将军2的视角看 两种情况的结果是不一样的
they look very different from general 2's point of view.
我们现在来尝试设计一个算法
So, let's try to design an algorithm,
帮助两位将军在这种场景下成功协调进攻时间
which will nevertheless get the two generals into agreement.
我们先从将军1的角度来研究一下这个问题
And so, let's think about it first of all from the point of view of general 1.
将军1基本上只有两种可能的选择
General 1 basically has two choices,
将军1可以这样选择：不管是否收到响应 总发起进攻
either general 1 is going to always attack no matter whether any response is received,
将军1也可以这样选择：仅当收到将军2的响应后再发起进攻
or general 1 is going to wait and only attack if it receives a response from general 2.
我们先来讨论第一种选择
So, let's start with the first case.
第一种选择下 不管是否收到响应 将军1都会发起进攻
So, general 1 always attacks even if no response is received.
这种情况下 将军1希望确定将军2也会发起进攻
So, in this case, general 1 wants to make sure that general 2 is also going to attack,
否则 将军1就会面临困境
because otherwise, general 1 is going to be in a problematic situation.
我们可以这么做
So, we could say that
将军1向将军2一次又一次的发送消息
general 1 is going to send lots and lots and lots of messengers over to general 2,
所有消息内容都是“现在进攻”，“进攻”，“进攻”
all saying “Attack at this time”, “Attack”, “Attack”.
如果有一条消息传输成功 那就没问题了
And if one of those gets through, then things are probably OK,
因为将军2知道将军1总会发起进攻
because general 2 knows that general 1 is always going to attack.
因此 将军2知道
So, general 2 knows that
即使将军1没有收到自己的回复 将军2仍可发起进攻 将军2总是安全的
it's safe for general 2 to also go into battle even without responding to general 1,
因为将军1承诺他一定会发起进攻
because after all, general 1 has promised that general 1 is always going to attack.
然而 也有可能出现所有消息都丢失的情况
However, it could happen that all of the messengers are lost.
在这种情况下 将军2不知道要发起进攻
And so, in this case, general 2 does not know about the attack.
此时 将军1独木难支 惨遭失败
So, general 1 ends up going into battle alone and loses.
这种情况的存在意味着将军1“总是进攻”的第一个选择没那么好
So, that means this first option of general 1 always attacking is not really great.
我们来考虑另一个选择
So, let's consider the alternative, which is that
将军1不承诺总是进攻
general 1 does not promise to always attack,
只有当收到将军2发来的积极响应后 将军1才会发起进攻
but general 1 will only attack if it receives a positive response from general 2.
在这种情况下 将军1是安全的
And in this case, general 1 is safe,
因为将军1知道 只有当确定将军2发起进攻时 自己才会发起进攻
because general 1 knows that it will only go into battle if general 2 is going into battle.
但此时 我们站在将军2的视角再来想一想
But now, if you think about it from general 2’s point of view,
现在 将军2知道 仅当将军1收到自己发送的响应后
now general 2 knows that general 1 will only go into attack
将军1才会发起进攻
if the response from general 2 to general 1 gets through,
因为将军1会等待另一位将军的响应
because after all, general 1 is waiting for that response from number 2.
现在
And so, now,
将军2所面临的处境和将军1在第一种选择下的处境是一致的
the general 2 is in exactly the same situation as general 1 was in the first option.
此时 将军2要不就承诺一定会进攻
And that is, either general 2 must commit to always attack,
此时将军2将会面临独木难支的风险
in which case, he risks being alone in the battle,
将军2要不就等待将军1的响应
or general 2 will wait for a response from general 1,
但此时 将军1又必须要响应了
but now, general 1 has to reply.
因此 我们最终会得到一个无穷无尽的死循环
And so, you end up with these potentially infinite chains of,
“是的 是的 我会发起进攻”、“好的 只要你发起进攻 我就发起进攻”
“Yes, yes, I'm going to attack”, “OK, I'm going to attack if you attack”,
“好的 我会发起进攻的 但只有你发起进攻我才会发起”
“Yes, OK, I will attack but only if you also attack”,
“好的 好的 我说过我会发起进攻了” 如此循环下去
“Yes, yes, I already said I'm going to attack”, and so on.
他们不得不互相发送响应消息
And so, they have to send each other back and forth these messages.
无法保证双方一定已经收到消息并发起进攻
You get actually an infinite chain
他们会陷入到无穷无尽的死循环中
before there's any certainty that they're actually both going to attack together.
在分布式系统中 这个问题被称为
And so, this is called in distributed systems the problem of
无共同知识
having no common knowledge.
系统中不存在下述共同知识
So, there's no knowledge in the system that
一个节点知道
one node knows,
另一个节点知道第一个节点知道
and the other node knows that the first node knows it.
第一个节点知道第二个节点知道第一个节点知道
And the first node knows that the second node knows that the first node knows it,
以此类推
and so on.
你可以一直往下、无穷无尽地构造下去
So, you can construct these arbitrary chains.
最终的结果是
And the end result is just that
无论我们互相之间发送和接收多少次消息 只要消息次数是有限的
no matter how many finite sequences of messages we send back and forth,
我们就永远无法绝对保证
we never actually have absolute certainty that
当且仅当将军2发起进攻时 将军1才发起进攻
general 1 is going to attack if and only if general 2 is going to attack.
你可以构建概率性的保证机制 概率可以无限接近于1
So, you can build up gradually increasing, like probabilistic certainty maybe,
具体机制依赖于消息是否会被截获的相关系统假设
depending on your assumptions of whether messengers get captured or not.
但我们不可能做到100%的保证
But it's actually impossible to reach complete certainty here.
现在 我们把这个抽象的思想实验应用到具体的例子中
Now, let's take this abstract thought experiment and apply it to a concrete example.
我们在上一节课程中介绍过一个例子
So, we had in the last lecture this example of
在线商店向支付服务发起一个RPC请求
an online shop making an RPC request to a payment service
让用户可以使用信用卡支付
in order to charge a credit card.
在这个场景下 我们希望做到的是
And really what we want here is that
当且仅当客户为货品支付费用 在线商店才会发货
the online shop dispatches the goods if and only if the customer pays for the goods,
大家可以想象一下 如果在线商店已经发货
because you can imagine if the online shop dispatches the goods
但支付服务没有从客户的信用卡划账
but the payment service does not charge the credit card,
那在线商店就不高兴了
then the shop is unhappy,
因为商店相当于免费给客户发送了商品
because the shop has just given away some goods for free.
如果在线商店没有发货
If the online shop does not dispatch the goods,
但支付服务已经从客户的信用卡划账了
but the payment service does charge the credit card,
这时候客户就不高兴了
then the customer is unhappy,
因为客户花了钱 但没收到任何商品
because the customer got charged without receiving any goods.
我们实际想达到的目标
So, really what we want is
与两将军问题所要实现的目标是高度类似的
something that looks extremely similar to the two generals problem here,
当且仅当支付服务从客户的信用卡划账后
that the online shop dispatches to goods
在线商店才会发货
if and only if the payment service charges the card.
正如大家所想象的那样
And as you can imagine,
在线商店和支付服务的RPC
the RPC between the online shop and the payment service looks very much like
和两将军问题中穿梭在丛林的信使非常相似
the messengers running through the forest in the two generals problem,
消息可能会丢失
which is to say that the messages might get lost,
其中一方可能无法收到消息
either one or the other might get lost.
因此 实际上不可能让在线商店和支付服务
And so, it is actually not possible for the online shop and the payment service
以100%的概率保证
to achieve the certainty that
当前仅当一个动作发生后 另一个动作才会发生
one action will happen if and only if the other action happens.
当然了 实际中的在线商店仍然可以运作
In practice, actually of course, online shops do work.
但在线商店可以运作的原因是
But the reason they work is because
有很多第二层的保护机制来保证支付和发货过程可以合理运作
there are a bunch of second level safeguards then, which ensure a reasonable outcome.
例如 有可能出现信用卡已经完成了支付
So, for example, if it turns out that the card got charged
但在线商店的仓库里已经没货了
but the online shop doesn't actually have the goods in stock anymore,
此时 在线商店只需要发送一封致歉邮件 内容是
then the online shop will just send an apology email saying,
“很抱歉 我们的仓库没货了 我们会向您的信用卡退款”
“Oh sorry, actually we're out of stock. We've refunded your card”.
这种解决方案就很不错
And so, that way it's fine.
因此 在线商店场景可以走出两将军问题的困境
And so, it's possible to get out of this situation
因为支付过程是可撤销的 可以执行退款操作
because the charge is actually a revocable action. It's possible to refund the charge.
因此 我们总可以让客户有安全感
And therefore, it's possible to get back into a safe state
就算支付成功但在线商店没有发货 客户也能通过退款来获取安全感
where neither the goods dispatch nor the payment has effectively happened.
另一种情况是支付服务有可能没有成功从客户信用卡上划账
Or another option is that the payment service may or may not have charged a card.
这种情况下 当网络被修复后
And so, when the network is repaired,
当消息又能传输成功时
and the messages can get through again,
在线商店可以向支付服务发起检查请求 询问到
then the online shop checks with the payment service saying,
“你现在成功划款了吗？之前我没收到你划款成功的响应”
“Now, did you actually charge that card or not, because I never heard back from you”,
“你是否完成划款操作了？”
“Whether you charge it or not”?
这种情况下 大概率发生的事情是
And so, what will probably happen is that
即使支付服务不能确定在线商店是否发货
the payment service will always go ahead and charge the card,
支付服务也可以执行划款操作
even if it's not certain that the online shop is going to dispatch the goods,
这么做也没问题 因为必要时 支付服务仍然可以发起退款
in this case it's fine, because the payment could get refunded if necessary.
这就是在线商店问题
So, that is the way in which this online shopping problem
与两将军问题不完全一致的地方
is not actually exactly the same as the two generals problem.
尽管如此 两将军问题也演示了
But nevertheless, the two generals problem does illustrate this issue of
分布式系统中存在的不确定性
uncertainty that we have in a distributed system
即我们无法确定消息是否真的成功传输给了对方
when we're not sure if the messages got through or not.